Finding Aid for Mary Shurtleff collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary Shurtleff collection 1848-1915 (scattered dates)
Shurtleff, Mary Belle, collector
1 linear foot, 1 outsized folder, and 275 MB
861078 Aa 2 UAl
Collector of Cross Village, Michigan materials. Collection consists of business records for a general store, land patents made to members of the Native American community, a letter and photograph of Catholic priest N. Louis Sifferath, a panorama of the village waterfront, and a plat map of Cross Village Township.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mary Shurtleff (Donor no. 7267 ) and Jane Talcott (Donor no. 7808 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Cross Village is located in northwest Emmet County, Michigan. Over the course of its history it has been variously known as Waganakisi, Anamiewatigoing, L'Arbre Croche, Old Arbre Croche, LaCroix, and Cross Village, after its namesakes, a crooked tree and a large cross in the village.
The Ottawa inhabited the village beginning in the late seventeenth or early eighteenth century. A Jesuit mission was also established in the village, though abandoned in the late eighteenth century. In the nineteenth century Catholic priests once again served in the village including Father Francis Pierz (1830s), Father Ignatius Mrak (1840s to mid-1850s), Father Seraphim Zorn (late 1850s), Father Loius Sifferath (1860s), and Father John Bernard Weikamp (1855-1889).
Treaties between the United States Government and the Ottawa and Chippewa (several of whom had moved to Cross Village sometime after 1830) resulted in them being granted tracts of land in the area during the mid-to-late nineteenth century. One early initiative was to move the village from the shore to the bluff. In the late 1840s, several Ottawa pooled their resources and gave their chief, Joseph Nawimashkote "full power to purchase land for use at the cross, that we may own it in common" (Shurtleff, 1963, p. 11). Upon his death, the land was to be redistributed to those who had contributed to its acquisition.
Members of the Shurtleff family first moved to Cross Village in 1870. Captain John Wagley, who himself had come to Cross Village in 1865, had established the first district school in Emmet County and engaged John S. Shurtleff to teach there. Two of Shurtleff's sons, Orville Homer and William Melville, went into business together in Cross Village and built a store in 1883. Mary Belle Shurtleff was William's daughter. She wrote a history of Cross Village, Old Arbre Croche, published in 1933, 1945, 1955, and 1963, and also collected various historical documents related to the village.
_________________________
Resources:
Shurtleff, Mary Belle. Old Arbre Croche: a factual and comprehensive history of Cross Village, Michigan. [Michigan: s.n.], 1963. Available in HathiTrust, http://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015071304110
"Village of Cross Village." In The Traverse Region, Historical And Descriptive, With Illustrations of Scenery And Portraits And Biographical Sketches of Some of Its Prominent Men And Pioneers, 141-144. Chicago: H. R. Page, 1884. Available in HathiTrust, http://hdl.handle.net/2027/miun.bad0776.0001.001
Shurtleff, Benjamin. Descendants of William Shurtleff San Francisco: R. L. Shurtleff, 1976. Available in HathiTrust, http://hdl.handle.net/2027/wu.89066307901
The Mary Shurtleff collection consists of documents and images relating to Cross Village and its inhabitants. The collection is arranged in 3 series: Business records, Other collected documents, and Visual materials.
Subjects:
Business records.; Cross Village (Mich.); General stores--Michigan--Cross Village.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Government relations--Michigan.; Land grants--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cross Village (Mich.)--Lumber industry.; Cross Village (Mich.)--Waterfronts.; Land subdivision--Michigan--Cross Village.; Lumber industry--Michigan--Cross Village.; Sifferath, N. L.; Waterfronts--Michigan--Cross Village.
Contributors:
Sifferath, N. L.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Plats (maps).
- Business records
  The Business records series (8 bound volumes, late 1800s-1915) contains volumes of various financial records from the Shurtleff family general store in Cross Village.
  - Daybook, 1903-1904 (Box 1)
  - Financial records of items by category, late 1800s (Box 1)
  - Record book of accounts paid by name and month, 1900 (Box 1)
  - Shurtleff's automobile expenses, 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - Financial records of items by category as well as lists of "personal property on farm", "real estate" and "fixtures", late 1800s (Box 1)
  - Ledgers, 1903-1905, 3 volumes (Box 1)
- Other collected documents
  The Other collected documents series (2 folders, 1848-1878) consists of ten land patents and a letter from N. Louis Shifferath, a Catholic priest who served in Cross Village. The patents were issued as a result of treaties between the Ottawa and Chippewa nations and the U.S. Government. Recipients include Joseph Nawimash Kota (4 patents), Catharine Ka no ji, Michel Nau e mush cotta, Margaret Benisse-wat-o-no-quay, Joseph Shaw gwaw baw no, Mary Pe naw do way quay, and Josette Paw ge nay.
  - Land patents to Cross Village Indians, 1848-1878 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Father N. Louis Sifferath to W. Shurtleff and friends, 1871 (Box 1)
- Visual materials
  The Visual materials series (3 folders and 275 MB, ca. 1890-ca. 1900) includes a portrait of N. Louis Shifferath, a panoramic view of the Cross Village waterfront (in digital format), and a plat map for Cross Village Township (in digital format).
  - Portrait of Fr. N. Louis Sifferath (photograph; includes note on his background), ca. 1890s (Box 1)
  - Panoramic view of Cross Village Township, Mich. (showing sawmill and waterfront), ca. 1890s (Folder 1)
  - Plat map showing land ownership of Cross Village Township, Mich., ca. 1900
    (digiital file only, original retiined by donor)